<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Francfort, concerning the election of the most mighty Emperor Matthias the first of that name who was elected and crowned in Francfort, in Iune last, anno. 1612. Translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112460</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847714</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 815:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Francfort, concerning the election of the most mighty Emperor Matthias the first of that name who was elected and crowned in Francfort, in Iune last, anno. 1612. Translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Eld] for Henry Holland, and are to be sold at his shop in Iuy lane, at the signe of the Holy-bush,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf verso contains "The Emperors stile and titles, as he was proclaimed in Francfort: the 13. of Iune 1612".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Matthias, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1557-1619.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="form_of_imperial_address">
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:2"/>
            <p>The Emperors Stile and Titles, as he was proclaimed in Francfort: the 13. of Iune 1612.</p>
            <p>MATTHIAS, by the grace of God, of that name the firſt: the moſt high, moſt mighty, &amp; most ſacred <hi>EMPEROR</hi> of Romans.</p>
            <p>KING of Germanie, Hungarie, Bohemia, Dalmatia, Croatia and Sclauonia:</p>
            <p>ARCHDVKE of Auſtria, DVKE of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie, Stiria, Carinthia, Carniola, Wirtenbergh, and of both high and low Sileſia:</p>
            <p>MARQVESSE of Morauia, and of high and low Luſatia: COVNT or ERLE of Habspourgh, Tirole and Tecce, &amp;c. our moſt mild Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEWES From Francfort, Concerning the election of the moſt mighty Emperor <hi>Matthias</hi> the firſt of that name, Who was elected and crowned in Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, in Iune last, Anno. 1612.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>the double-headed eagle as German imperial device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Henry Holland,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Iuy lane at the ſigne of the Holy-buſh. 1612.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12771:3"/>
            <head>Newes from Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford ford concerning the Election of <hi>the most mighty Emperour,</hi> Matthias.</head>
            <p>RVDOLPHVS the ſecond, Sonne of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> and of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, borne in Vienna the 18. of Iuly the yeare of our Lord 1552. was elected Emperour the yeare 1576. at Ratisbone, and continued in his gouernement vntill this laſt yeare 1611.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rudolphus</hi> was a Prince that tooke more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light light in rare work-manſhip and artificiall deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at home, then in warlike affaires abroad, contrary to his poefie A.D.S.I.T which is, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juvante, Domino, Superabo, Imperatorem, Turca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12771:4"/>In Engliſh; by Gods helpe I will ouercome the Emperor of the Turkes.</p>
            <p>His brother <hi>Matthias</hi> Arch-Duke of Auſtria, &amp;c. the third Sonne of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> ſucceeded by Election in his ſteed the 23. of Iune 1612.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matthias</hi> is a Prince of great experience and courage: for, ſince the yeare 1577. hee hath beene trained vp in the managing of great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: He was brought in ſecretly, and afterwards publikely receiued to the Gouernment of the Low Countries, with certaine conditions wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hee agreed the 20. of Ianuary 1577. (the Prince of Orange remaining his Lieutenant Generall:) but ſeeing the confuſion which roſe dayly, hee tooke his leaue of them the 21. of October 1581. Hauing learned there, as in a Schoole, many things whereof ſince hee hath made very good vſe.</p>
            <p>He did ſee of late, in the yeare 1608. what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did begin to riſe in the Empire, by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions which were practiſed in diuers places for the reformed religions ſake, &amp; how that by the Councell of Ieſuites, Ieſuited Gouernours
<pb facs="tcp:12771:4"/>were brought in; wherby the antient Priuileges and liberties of conſcience were troden vnder foote, and by their mutuall ſtrife the Turke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged; and how the Arch-Duke <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of Stiria was brought in to be preferred before him at the Diet of Regensbourgh. Hence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on due confiderations and conſultations, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe leſſe partiall in Religion, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuller in mind, The Nobles and confederats of Hungary, Auſtria, Morauia, Sileſia, &amp;c. did chooſe <hi>Matthias</hi> for their head, brought toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a competent Armie, and eſtabliſhed liberty of Religion, and the vſe of the ancient Priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in all thoſe Countries: This Army beeing arrayed, <hi>Matthias</hi> marched with it towards Prague in Bohemia, for to conferre with the Emperour his brother, who by the Ieſuiticall practiſes kept himſelfe cloſe, ſcarſe knowing how matters went, yet this Armie brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them no ſmal terrour, and maters were ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo reſolued vpon, that <hi>Matthias,</hi> beeing the elder brother, ſhould ſucceed in all the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Emperour, granting vnto him the
<pb facs="tcp:12771:5"/>Crowne of Hungary, and the command of Auſtria, Morauia and other dominions, yet in his life time: vnto the which hee had procured the peace with the Turke and the liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, giuing a free paſſage vnto the goſpell.</p>
            <p>The States of Bohemia did like ſo well of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> proceedings, that, they oppoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the wicked and ſiniſter practiſes of <hi>Leopold,</hi> did lik wiſe receiue him for their king granting vnto the Emperour his pallace, and a large reuenue to end his dayes in peaceably, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring not to be any longer abuſed by thoſe that crept in to the ouerthrow of their Eſtate. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> by theſe aduancements was the next in hope and apparance to the Imperiall Crowne. Therefore the Emperour <hi>Rudolphus</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond his brother beeing dead, Hee as firſt Elector, King of Bohemia, accompanied with the Queene his wife, met with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Electors, both ſpirituall and temporall at Francfort on the Mayne, which is an ancient Imperiall Citty, where the Election is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be made, and by the way, He war royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:12771:5"/>entertained by all thoſe Princes and Citties which lay in his paſſage, the Biſhop of <hi>Wirtz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> did receiue him in a great Hall, garniſhed with red veluet, amounting to the value of 30000. Florins.</p>
            <p>The King <hi>Matthias</hi> beeing arriued at <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> the three and twentith of May, &amp; the other Electors alſo in great ſtate, with very faire hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Equipage. The Magiſtrate of Francfort caufed a proclamation to bee made the 25.<note place="margin">Bourgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter.</note> of May, and read at euery ſtreet corner, whereby all the Cittizens were cited to appeare the next day at a publick and large market called the <hi>Romer,</hi> where King <hi>Matthias</hi> and the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces came,<note place="margin">Or Burſe.</note> and in their preſence did give their oaths, lifting vp their fingers; firſt, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and afterward the Cittizens, to defend the Princes from all inuaſions and tumults, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their power; this beeing done, they went to their ſeuerall lodgings.</p>
            <p>The ix. of Iune was the day appointed for the Election of a new Emperor, but the Electors could not well agree amongſt themſelues for
<pb facs="tcp:12771:6"/>the time, and matters were deferred vntill the Wedneſday following; the occaſion of their diſagreement, was becauſe the three ſpirituall. Electors, Mentz, Trier, and Colen, with the Duke of Saxone, whoſe minde was peruerted by ſome ſiniſter meanes, did iudge the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke <hi>Albert,</hi> yonger brother of <hi>Matthias,</hi> fitter for the Empire then King <hi>Matthias</hi> who is ſubiect to the gout, they ſaid, and not like to liue long: This proiect ſeemed very ſtrange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt for vnto the Duke of Zwebrough, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator of the Palatinat,<note place="margin">Dux Bipon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inus.</note> and vnto Lord Putlitz deputie of the Duke of Brandenbourgh, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the common opinion of the moſt part of all the Princes of Chriſtendome, that <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> was farre the fitter man, in regarde of his vnderſtanding, experience, courage and ſtate, and that doubtleſſe, ſome ſecret corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did bend their hearts and voyce towards <hi>Albertus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This delay being made, the Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in their meeting at Offenbach, a Towne neere vnto Francfort, hauing there alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:12771:6"/>Ambaſſadour of France Monſieur <hi>Ancell,</hi> for to conferre with alſo, did diſcouer the miſchiefs which were hidden vnder the deſired election of <hi>Albert,</hi> beeing meere practiſes of the Ieſuites and their adherents: but all was ouerthrowne: Firſt, by the reſolution of the Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who were ready to ſet the Imperiall crowne on <hi>Matthias</hi> his head, euen with their ſwords.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by a letter ſent from the French King and Queene his Mother, whereby <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> was recommended vnto the Electors, as the fitter man for the place.</p>
            <p>This letter beeing read, and the reſolution of the Prince of Anhalt, Lantgraue of Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, Duke of Wirtenbourgh, Marqueſſe of Baden, beeing knowne, the pluralitie of voyces in the next meeting, fell on <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth of Iune, the Bourgomaiſter of Francfort cauſed to bee denounced with the Drumme the day of the Election, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all ſtrangers, (the Electors onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) to voide the Citie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12771:7"/>
The xiii. day, about ſeuen a clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Electors with King <hi>Matthias</hi> went to the Councel chamber, ſtaid together one houre, did put on their princely garments, and rode from thence to the Church of Saint <hi>Barthol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew:</hi> Firſt the Archbiſhop of Mentz and Trier rode together: then followed the Archbiſhop of Colen, on the right hand, and <hi>Matthias</hi> on the left; after him came the Duke of Saxone, with a bare ſword in his hand,<note place="margin">Dux Bipon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inus.</note> The Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator of the Palatinat caried the Spheare of the World, and the Lord Putlitz in the name of the Duke of Brandenb. bore the Scepter: they beeing entred into the Church, euery one tooke his due place, which was noted with golden letters: the places for <hi>Mentz, Palatine,</hi> and King <hi>Matthias,</hi> were on the right hand, for Colen, Saxone, and Brandenbourgh, on the left, Trier was in the midſt. Then began the Prieſts to ſay the Maſſe <hi>de Sancto Spiritu:</hi> The temporall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors during the Celebration of the Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall Maſſe, retired vnto a Conclaue, or cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and it beeing ended, did returne vnto their
<pb facs="tcp:12771:7"/>roomes or places, and thence went, as their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der required, to the Altar, and tooke their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed oath, the ſpirituall Electors ſwearing, held their hands on their breſts, and the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall on the Goſpell. Thence they all went into a chamber, where the Votes were collected, which fell on <hi>Mathias, vnanimiter.</hi> This beeing performed, the new choſen King of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, was brought againe before the Altar, and all the Electors round about him, then was ſung <hi>Te Deum laudamus,</hi> all the Bels were rong, and the Ordenance diſcharged, in ſigne of ioy; from the Altar hee was led to a Royall Chaire, and then was proclaimed <hi>King of the Romaines, and Emperor apparant, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied to his Court, the gates of the Citty were opened, and xvi. of the chiefe Princes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie came to congratulate vnto him this dignitie.</p>
            <p>The Sunday following was the day of his Coronation, the Crowne was fetcht from Ake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Aquiſgra<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where it is kept in cuſtody, and diuers reliques were ſent along with the ſame, as, <hi>the bloud of
<pb facs="tcp:12771:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12771:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12771:9"/>Saint Stephan,</hi> &amp;c. leauing yet behind <hi>the bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>the ſmock of our Lady,</hi> which are held there in no ſmall deuotion.</p>
            <p>In the Marker place of <hi>Francfort</hi> was roaſted a whole Oxe, whereof a peece beeing cut off for the Emperour, the reſt was giuen to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, which did ſo throng, that two men were ſmothered to death, and ſix more ſorely hurt. There was alſo erected an Eagle of a huge big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">An Eagle being the Armes of the Empire.</note> out of which did run both red and white wine in aboundance. Finally, gold and ſiluer coynes were diſperſed amongſt the people, in great meaſure, and there followed very great feaſting, banqueting, melodious Muſick, &amp;c. Theſe ſolemnities beeing thus performed, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Coronation of the Empreſſe his wife: they returned towards Prague; beeing chiefly entertained and receiued with great honor and triumph in Norembergh.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot vnderſtand that the Popes Nuncio hath had any thing to doe with this election, which doubtleſſe his Holineſſe will not ſo well like of: But our hope is, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:12771:9"/>to the admonition of <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> Ann. 1420. (ſpeaking againſt that forged and ſuppoſed donation of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> whereon the Popes pride and vſurpation is grounded,) The Emperor will one day remember his ancient and lawfull authority, wherby he was to chooſe the Romiſh Biſhops, and not they to chooſe the Emperors, that his ſeate ought to bee in Rome, beeing Romane Emperor, and not to leaue it to the Vſurper, calling the ſame <hi>Peters Patrimonie. Conſtantine</hi> had no reaſon to giue it to that Prelate, who had leſſe warrant to receiue the ſame from him. Our Sauiour ſaid to <hi>Peter, I will giue thee the Keyes of Heauen:</hi> and it was the voyce of Sathan, <hi>I will giue thee theſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes with their glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Animaduertite Reges, eruditionem percipite O Iudices terrae.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
